Dr Michael Smith

School of Physics and Astronomy, University of Nottingham, Nottingham, NG7 2RD

www.nottingham.ac.uk/-ppzmis E-mail: mike.i.smith@nottingham.ac.uk

Tel: 0115 9515162 Researcher ID: B-4036-2011

Education

2004-2008 PhD in Physics, School of Physics & Astronomy, University of

Nottingham

(Supervisors: Dr James S. Sharp & Prof Clive J. Roberts)

2000-2004 MPhys in Physics (1st Class), School of Physics & Astronomy,

University of Manchester.

Career Highlights

Explanation of the physical mechanism behind the anti-rebound effect of droplets of dilute polymer solution. This resulted in a publication in *Physical Review Letters* which was highlighted as an Editor's suggestion and featured in *'Physics - Spotlighting exceptional Research'*, May 2010. Discussing this work in his plenary lecture at the 18th Ostwald Kolloquium, Professor Jens Eggers described it as "...some of the best experiments on drop impact ever".

- Awarded a Royal Society University Research Fellowship
- Principal Investigator funding awards totalling ~ £1.4 million

Research Interests

My research interests centre on understanding how the interactions of particles in a fluid give rise to their collective larger scale structures and properties,

- Dynamics / rheology of concentrated colloidal fluids
- Film formation in colloidal suspensions
- Quasi-2D granular fluids
- The anti-rebound phenomenon in dilute polymer solutions

Career Outline

- Proleptic lectureship, School of Physics, University of Nottingham (2016)
- Royal Society University Research Fellow (2012-Present), School of Physics, University of Nottingham
- Postdoctoral Research Associate (2009-2012),
 School of Physics, University of Nottingham (Employer: Dr James Sharp),
- Postdoctoral Research Associate, (2008-2009) School of Engineering, University of Edinburgh (Employer: Dr Volfango Bertola),
- PhD in Physics, (2004-2008)
 School of Physics & Astronomy, University of Nottingham (Supervisors: Dr James Sharp & Prof Clive Roberts)
- MPhys in Physics 1st Class, (2000-2004)
 School of Physics & Astronomy, University of Manchester

Prizes and awards

Royal Society University Research Fellowship 'Extensional flow and jamming of concentrated colloidal suspensions' Oct 2012

Best poster award – Institute of Physics Polymer Physics Group Biennial, University of Surrey, 12-14th Sept 2011 "Coloured Spherulites"

Best paper award – Institute for Liquid Atomization and Spray Systems 2010, Brno, Czech Republic, 6-8 Sept 2010 "The anti-rebound effect of flexible polymers on impacting drops"

Funding

-	
Royal Society Enhancement Award Dynamic Fluctuations in Granular Fluids (12/2017)	£81,092.00
EPSRC ICase PhD studentship Dynamic break-up in glassy fluids (10/2017)	£111,096.00
Royal Society University Research Fellowship Renewal "Dynamic Fluctuations and Break-up in Glassy Particle Fluids" (10/2017)	£356,408.00
ESRF X-ray Beam time "Shear band formation in a drying colloidal film" (12/2016)	~£25,822.20
EPSRC-Royal Society fellowship engagement "Ageing, film formation and cracking in colloidal glasses" (11/2013)	£332,590.00

NNNC Early Career Research Competition

£2,000.00

Equipment time in Nottingham nanoscience & constant = (15/01 - 31/03/2013)

Royal Society University Research Fellowship

£543,720.64

"Extensional flow and jamming in concentrated colloidal suspensions" (10/2012)

Named Researcher: STFC ISIS neutron scattering time

~ £27,000.00

Publications

1. 'Shear bands and the evolving microstructure in a drying colloidal film studied with scanning u-SAXS'

B. Yang, N. D. Smith, A. Johannes, M. Burghammer, M. I. Smith, Sci. Rep. 8, 12979 (2018)

- 2. 'Boundary effects in a quasi-two-dimensional driven granular fluid' N.D. Smith, M.I. Smith, *Physical Review E 96:062910 (2017)*
- 3. 'Interplay of Crack Hopping, Delamination and Interface Failure in Drying Nanoparticle Films'

B. Yang, J.S. Sharp, M.I. Smith, Sci. Rep. 6:32296 (2016)

4. 'Fracture of Jammed Colloidal Suspensions'

M.I. Smith, Sci. Rep. 5:14175 (2015)

- 5. 'Mechanical vibrations of pendant liquid droplets' R.H. Temperton, M.I. Smith, J.S. Sharp Eur. Phys. J. E 38:79 (2015)
- 6. 'Shear Banding in Drying Colloidal Nanoparticles'

B. Yang, J.S. Sharp, M.I. Smith, ACS Nano 9:4077-4084 (2015)

- 7. 'Origin of contact line forces during the retraction of dilute polymer solution drops.' M.I. Smith, J.S. Sharp, Langmuir 30, 5455-9, (2014)
- 8. 'Giant Amyloid Spherulites reveal their true colours' M.I. Smith, J.S. Sharp, C.J. Roberts, Soft Matter 8, 3751-5 (2012)
- 9. 'Factors affecting the formation of Insulin Spherulites'

M.I. Smith, V. Fodera, J.S. Sharp, C.J. Roberts, A.M. Donald, *Colloids & Surfaces B: Biointerfaces 89, 216-222 (2011)*

10. 'The effects of substrate constraint on crack pattern formation in thin films of colloidal polystyrene particles'

M.I. Smith, J.S. Sharp, Langmuir 27, 8009 (2011)

11. 'Dilatancy in the flow and fracture of stretched colloidal suspensions'

M.I. Smith, R. Besseling, M.E. Cates, V. Bertola, *Nature Communications*. 1, 114 (2010)

(Featured in "Science Daily" under the title 'Smashing fluids – the physics of flow', Dec 2010)

12. 'Particle Velocimetry inside Newtonian and non-Newtonian droplets impacting a hydrophobic surface'

M.I. Smith, V. Bertola, *Experiments in Fluids 50, 1385-1391* (2010)

13. 'Effect of polymer additives on the wetting of impacting droplets'

M.I. Smith, V. Bertola, Physical Review Letters 104, 154502 (2010)

(Highlighted as Editor's suggestion – Featured in "Physics – spotlighting exceptional research", May 2010)

- 14. 'Insulin fibril nucleation: the role of prefibrillar aggregates' M.I. Smith, J.S. Sharp & C.J. Roberts, *Biophysical J. 95 3400-3406 (2008)*
- 15. Nucleation and Growth of Insulin Fibrils in Bulk Solution and at Hydrophobic Polystyrene Interfaces' M.I. Smith, J.S. Sharp & C.J. Roberts, *Biophysical J. 93, 2143-2151 (2007)*
- 16. 'Spinodal wrinkling in thin-film poly(ethylene oxide)/polystyrene bilayers' J.S. Sharp, D. Vader, J.A. Forrest, M.I. Smith, M. Khomenko & K. Dalnoki-Veress, Eur. Phys. J. E 19, 423-432 (2006)

Conference Papers

'The anti-rebound effect of flexible polymers on impacting drops'
 M.I. Smith, V. Bertola, Proc. 23rd European Conference on Liquid Atomization and Spray Systems, Brno, Czech Republic, 6 -8 September 2010.

(ILASS 2010 best paper award)

2. 'Velocity measurements inside impacting drops of dilute polymer solutions,' M.I. Smith, V. Bertola, DIPSI Workshop 2010 on droplet impact phenomena and spray investigation, Bergamo, Italy 27 -28 May 2010.

Invited Talks

• <u>M.I. Smith</u>, Drying Days Conference, Toulouse 'The interplay of instabilities in a drying colloidal film (23-24th March 2017)

Invited Seminars

- <u>M.I. Smith</u>, Materials Physics seminar, University of Durham, 'Stretching dense colloidal suspensions: from flow to fracture' (14th January 2015).
- M.I. Smith, Polymer physics seminar, University of Sheffield, 'Watching paint dry (& crack)' (6th Dec 2013)
- M.I. Smith, J.S.Sharp, C.J. Roberts, Polymer physics seminar, University of Sheffield, 'Nucleation and growth of insulin fibrils' (21st March 2008)

Conference presentations - Oral

- M.I. Smith, American Physical Society, New Orleans 'The interplay of instabilities in a drying colloidal film (13-17th March 2017)
- <u>M.I. Smith</u>, American Physical Society, Baltimore *'The flow and fracture of concentrated colloidal suspensions (14-18th March 2016)*
- B. Yang, J.S. Sharp, <u>M.I. Smith</u>, European Coating Symposium 2015, Eindhoven, Netherlands (9-11th September 2015) 'Shear banding in drying colloidal films'
- M.I. Smith, R. Besseling, A. Schofield, J.S. Sharp, M.E. Cates, V. Bertola, American Physical Society, Boston, USA (27th February – 2nd March 2012) 'Stretching dense suspensions from flow to fracture'
- M.I. Smith, V. Bertola, Institute of Physics: Biennial meeting of the polymer physics group,
 University of Surrey, (12-14th September 2011) 'Controlling droplet impact by polymer additives'
- M.I. Smith, R. Besseling, A. Schofield, J.S. Sharp, M.E. Cates, V. Bertola, 8th Liquid Matter Conference, Universitat Wien, Austria (5-10th September 2011) *'Stretching Dense Colloidal Suspensions: from flow to fracture'*
- M.I. Smith, V. Bertola, Institute of Physics: Condensed Matter and materials physics, University of Warwick (14-16th December 2010) 'Controlling droplet impact by polymer additives'
- <u>M.I. Smith,</u> J.S. Sharp, C.J. Roberts, Institute of Physics: Biennial meeting of the polymer physics group, University of Durham (10th-12th September 2007) 'Nucleation and Growth of Insulin Fibrils in Bulk Solution and at hydrophobic polystyrene interfaces'
- M.I. Smith, J.S. Sharp, C.J. Roberts, Institute of Physics: Interface of Medical and Biological Physics, University of Southampton (May 2007) 'Nucleation and Growth of Insulin Fibrils in Bulk Solution and at hydrophobic polystyrene interfaces'

Conference presentations - Poster

- <u>M.I. Smith</u>, J.S. Sharp, American Physical Society, Boston, USA (27th February 2nd March 2012) 'Cracking in thin films of colloidal particles on elastomeric substrates'
- M.I. Smith, J.S. Sharp, C.J. Roberts, American Physical Society, Boston, USA (27th February 2nd March 2012) 'Optical properties of large amyloid spherulites'

- <u>M.I. Smith</u>, V. Bertola, American Physical Society, Boston, USA (27th February 2nd March 2012) 'Controlling droplet impact with polymer additives'
- M.I. Smith, J.S. Sharp, Institute of Physics: Polymer Physics Group, University of Surrey, (12-14th September 2011) 'Crack formation in colloidal films: the role of substrate constraint'
- M.I. Smith, J.S. Sharp, Institute of Physics: Polymer Physics Group, University of Surrey, (12-14th September 2011) 'Coloured Spherulites'

(IOP PPG Biennial Best poster award)

- M.I. Smith, R. Besseling, A. Schofield, J.S. Sharp, M.E. Cates, V. Bertola, Institute of Physics: Polymer Physics Group, University of Surrey, (12-14th September 2011) 'Stretching colloidal suspensions: from flow to fracture
- <u>M.I. Smith,</u> V. Bertola, 8th Liquid Matter Conference, Universitat Wien, Austria (5-10th September 2011) 'Controlling droplet Impact with polymer additives'
- M.I. Smith, J.S. Sharp, 8th Liquid Matter Conference, Universitat Wien, Austria (5-10th September 2011) 'Cracking Colloids: the role of substrate constraint'
- M.I. Smith, V. Bertola, SET for Britain 2011, Houses of Parliament (14th March 2011) 'Making droplets stick'
- M.I. Smith, R. Besseling, M.E. Cates, V. Bertola, Institute of Physics: Condensed Matter and Material Physics, University of Warwick (14-16th December 2010) 'Stretching colloidal suspensions: from flow to fracture'
- M.I. Smith, J.S. Sharp, Institute of Physics: Condensed Matter and Material Physics, University of Warwick (14-16th December 2010) 'Cracking Colloids: the role of substrate constraint'
- M.I. Smith, V. Fodera, J.S. Sharp, A.M. Donald, C.J. Roberts, Institute of Physics: Condensed Matter and Material Physics, University of Warwick (14-16th December 2010) 'Towards an understanding of polymorphism in protein aggregation'
- M.I. Smith, V. Fodera, J.S. Sharp, A.M. Donald, C.J. Roberts, Institute of Physics: Physics meets
 Biology, University of Oxford (1st-3rd September 2010) 'Towards an understanding of polymorphism
 in protein aggregation'
- M.I. Smith, J.S. Sharp, C.J. Roberts, Institute of Physics: Self-assembling peptides, IOP London, (22nd March 2007) 'Nucleation and growth of insulin fibrils in bulk solution and at hydrophobic polystyrene interfaces'

Referee for International Journals

Physical Review Letters (3 papers), European Physical Journal E (2 paper), Soft Matter (3 papers), Experimental & Thermal Fluid Sci. (1 paper), J. Colloid & Int. Sci. (1 paper), Langmuir (2 paper), Physics of Fluids (1 paper)

Teaching Experience

Lecturer and Assessor, Force and Function at the Nanoscale (F33ON1) for 2nd Yr students (Autumn 2018-present)

Lecturer and Assessor, Modern Applications of Physics (F34AAP) for 4th Yr students (Spring 2017-current)

3rd Yr Laboratory Teaching (Autumn 2016)

Frontiers in physics lecture / problems class for 1st Year students (March 2013)

Co-convenor for "Materials, Microstructure & Microscopy" 4th year module (Spring 2011)

Supervision of Research projects

Postdocs:

Dr Bin Yang: Ageing, film formation and cracking in colloidal glasses" (Supervision of PGRA, University of Nottingham, 2013-Present)

Phds: Nathan Smith: "Interactions in a quasi-2D granular fluid" (2014-Present)

Matthew Hayes: "Dynamic break-up in glassy fluids" (EPSRC Icase studentship)

James Downs: "Phase transitions in a 2D granular fluid"

Masters Projects:

12 students on 4th year Masters projects.

Summer Internships:

8 summer internships

Outreach

- *'Introduction to Nanoscience'* –Sutton Trust widening participation summer school (July 2015 present) consisting of an introductory lecture and related laboratory practicals
- *'Introduction to Nanoscience'* Nottingham Potential widening participation summer school (July 2015 present) consisting of an introductory lecture and related laboratory practicals
- 'Seeing the unseeable' University of Nottingham widening participation campaign for sixth formers. Delivered introductory talk on nanoscience and lead UV-vis laboratory demonstration (11th February 2015)
- *'The electromagnetic spectrum'* University of Nottingham outreach to primary school children (Easter 2014)

Administration

- Member of the research committee (School of Physics, UoN, 2013-present)
- Nanoscience group meeting co-ordinator (2013-2016)

Referees

Dr James Sharp - School of Physics & Astronomy, University of Nottingham, NG7 2RD

e-mail: james.sharp@nottingham.ac.uk tel: 0115 9515142

Dr Volfango Bertola - Centre for Engineering Dynamics , University of Liverpool

e-mail: volfango.bertola@liverpool.ac.uk tel: 0151 794 4804